<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MHW on BCB R Stats Pages</title>
    <link>/tags/mhw/</link>
    <description>Recent content in MHW on BCB R Stats Pages</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/mhw/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Basic Detection and Visualisation of Events</title>
      <link>/project/basic_mhw_mcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/basic_mhw_mcs/</guid>
      <description>This material also appears as a heatwaveR vignette.
Data The detect_event() function is the core of this package, and it expects to be fed the output of the second core function, ts2clm(). By default, ts2clm() wants to receive a two-column dataframe with one column labelled t containing all of the date values, and a second column temp containing all of the temperature values. Please note that the date format it expects is “YYYY-MM-DD”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Downloading and Preparing NOAA OISST Data</title>
      <link>/project/oisst_prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/oisst_prep/</guid>
      <description>This material also appears as a heatwaveR vignette.
Overview In this vignette we will see how to retrieve and prepare Reynolds optimally interpolated sea surface temperature (OISST) data for calculating marine heatwaves (MHWs). The OISST product is a global 1/4 degree gridded dataset of Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) derived SSTs at a daily resolution, starting on 1 September 1981. The source of the data is currently the NOAA NCDC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Events in Gridded Data</title>
      <link>/project/gridded_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/gridded_data/</guid>
      <description>Overview In the previous vignette we saw how to download and prepare OISST data. In this vignette we will use the subsetted data we downloaded (not global) for our example on how to detect MHWs in gridded data.
library(dplyr) # For basic data manipulation library(ggplot2) # For visualising data library(heatwaveR) # For detecting MHWs library(tidync) # For easily dealing with NetCDF data library(doParallel) # For parallel processing  Loading data Because we saved our data as an .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
